Welcome back to the bugs of C++ series.
The series in which we take a look at
various bugs in C++ and how you can
avoid them. I often say that memory is
the most important thing in programming
particularly when it comes to low-level
languages like C and C++. Intrinsic to
memory management is lifetime. You need
to be aware of the lifetime of any
memory that you allocate. Now the
concept of memory might be a little bit
too raw too lowle. So you can always
picture this as [music] objects. What is
the lifetime of a given object that you
create in C++? Fundamentally, that
translates directly into memory.
However, it's a bit of a higher level
concept that may make more sense. This
whole memory management, lifetime
management situation is such a big deal
that it's one of the biggest selling
points of higher level languages. A
language like C or Java with a garbage
collector and stronger memory management
models is something called a managed
language. C++ is an unmanaged language.
It's up to you to manage everything. And
that's a lot of power. That's a lot of
power, but it's also a lot of
responsibility. And very often, it's
very easy to forget about this
responsibility and neglect it. But what
about things like smart pointers? What
about all of these constructs that we
[music] can build into the language
ourselves to make things happen more
automatically than they otherwise would?
Can't I just use them and then
everything will be sweet? Well, yeah,
they help, but they don't often solve
the problem entirely, especially if
you're not just picking the nuclear
option of just do everything for me. I
mean, you can write systems in C++ that
make it like a managed language and then
I guess a lot of these things would go
away. But the reason we're using an
unmanaged language here is because we
want that control and we're trying to
minimize overhead. So, it's a bit of a
balancing act and problems can still
happen even if you do use Smart
Pointers. And that's ultimately what
we're going to be taking a look at
today. What happens if we relax a little
bit and we let something slip through
the cracks? Let's take a look at an
example. What I have over here is some
code from my application architecture
series. We have some really simple code
here that will be called every frame
inside an on update function. And what
it does is transition to a different
layer from the current layer if a given
key is pressed. Layers are a way to
implement custom behavior in an
application. If you're not sure what
they are, check out the video I made on
layers up there. The transition to
function inside the base layer class
allows us to transition the current
layer into a new layer. Pardon
IntelliSense not working as always. So
in this case it lets us by pressing the
one key transition to another layer
which in this case is just a red clear
color and we can go back and forth
between them and that's also how this
switch button over here via an overlay
layer works as well. Software
engineering can get pretty overwhelming
and usually the complexity just grows
and grows. You try and keep things
simple, but as time goes on, it's really
hard to track everything in all of the
different tools that you use and make
sure that what you're doing actually
aligns [music] with everything else.
Miro, the sponsor of this video, is a
unified visual workspace for mapping
ideas, designing systems, and
collaborating in real time or
asynchronously. It's a great place to
model architecture, break down complex
problems, plan and track work, and
communicate technical decisions clearly
across the [music] whole team. With the
addition of Miro AI, this potentially
tedious task of translating the design
and architecture in your head to an
actual visual diagram that communicates
that well becomes much easier. I don't
know about you, but I'm not the biggest
fan of making diagrams. I'd rather write
some code. With Miro, I can just tell
the sidekick roughly what I want and it
produces really great diagrams in
seconds. Removing that friction of
getting a diagram going really helps
with team communication. Instead of
having a meeting, for example, to
discuss design, [music]
which first of all is already a bit of a
challenge if you have a global team
across many time zones, instead of that
meeting, Miro can help me effectively
communicate my ideas and design and make
sure my team is on the same page. I find
that I'm much more likely to do that
because Miro AI lets me do this quickly
without me feeling like I'm just
dragging these shapes and arrows around
instead of actually working. Of course,
I'm still working when I'm dragging
shapes around. It's obviously important
to design things, but you know what I
mean. For example, if I want a quick UML
diagram describing the design of my C++
application architecture series, I can
just type something like this and I've
already got most of the work done. You
can see it's generated what I've asked
along with some placeholder example
content that I can easily modify to suit
my needs. From there, I can refine it
again using AI or just start doing
things manually my way. I find this
really helps to unblock you from how do
I start this and actually get the ball
rolling, which honestly is invaluable.
Miro has like 300 plus templates for you
to start with. Over 2 and a half
thousand diagramming shapes as well as
direct integration with so many things,
Jira, Trello, Microsoft Teams, and
Google Meet. The list goes on. You can
embed diagrams into tools like Notion
and Confluence, which really helps as
well. Seriously, give Miro a try today.
Check out my link in the description
below and play around with it on your
next project. Huge thank you to Miro for
sponsoring this video. Cool. So, we have
a way to transition from one layer to
another. This app layer over here is
what you see rendering the flame, and it
transitions to a void layer, which is
simply that red clear color that you
saw. And crucially, what happens when we
transition from one layer to another is
we actually destroy the current layer
because it's no longer alive. It doesn't
need to be. We can release all the
resources allocated with that layer
because we don't need it anymore. We've
transitioned to another layer. So over
here in the destructor we have a log
message and then every time I switched
to another layer you can see it's
destroying that app layer then it's
going to recreate it again then it's
going to destroy it create it destroy it
etc every time we transition from one
layer to another now immediately what
you should be thinking about is okay
you're destroying the app layer
understandably because you don't need it
anymore you want to release those
resources and then potentially remake
them in the future but that process that
process of destruction you actually
deleting the app [clears throat] layer
and releasing all of those resources.
Where and when is that happening?
Because believe it or not, something as
simple as that consideration and
neglecting it can lead to not only your
application just flat out crashing, but
even things like security
vulnerabilities. So, let's dive a little
deeper into this transition function and
see how on earth it could cause so many
problems. So, at the moment, you can see
it calls this Q transition function. And
if we take a look at this, this is from
that layers video in my application
architecture series. This is what it
does. There's actually a to-do here
which I left in that series as well that
says don't do this. And this is really
the topic of discussion for today's
video. So what does this function do
exactly? Well, it grabs a layer stack
which is a vector of unique pointers
which are all of the layers inside our
application. It loops through all of
them to find which layer inside the data
structure is this current layer that
we're calling from. Once it finds it, it
replaces the current layer inside the
data structure with this new layer that
we would like to transition to. And then
it's done its job. So it returns
breaking out of the for loop and exiting
the function. Is this reasonable? I
mean, I think so. If this is all of the
context that you have, this is a pretty
normal function. I mean, I would
probably say that to an experienced C++
programmer, this would probably raise an
eyebrow and be like, hang on a minute.
But subjectively, I'd say it's fairly
subtle. And this is also why context is
so important in programming. It's also
one of the most important things.
Memory, lifetime, context, the list goes
on. It's a lot easier to see why this is
a problem when you consider the fact
that this gets called from this. So, we
are transitioning the current layer
inside the on update function of the
layer into another layer. Now if we have
the additional context of where this is
being called from and how exactly it
fits into what our application is doing
this frame then it becomes a lot clearer
to see the issue inside our main
application loop. We go through all of
the layers inside the layer stack and we
call this on update function over here
in app layer. One of the layers inside
that layer stack. We transition to
another layer which causes us to call
this code over here. We then find
ourselves inside this layer stack data
structure and then reassign ourselves.
This is a reference over here. So we're
reassigning the actual unique pointer
within layer stack into this other layer
that we're trying to transition to. Now
unique pointers are unique. There's one
owner of a unique pointer and in this
case it's clearly the layer stack. The
layer stack is a vector of unique
pointers. So this must be the only owner
of each and every layer. So if we have
layer at index zero, a layer at index
one, and then a layer at index two, and
then we're iterating through all of them
over here. We call on update on layer
number one, for example. And then within
that call stack, we reassign this layer
to be another different layer. And this
is the owner of that layer. That layer
is going to die. That layer is gone. and
we're putting in another layer at index
one. What this results in is this line
of code deleting the current layer while
we're actually still in its call stack.
So to demonstrate this a little bit more
visually, if I am in here and I press
the one key to transition to another
layer and we have a look at the call
stack. Here is the main application loop
inside application run. Then I go into
that specific layers on update function
that causes transition 2 to be called
and I'm inside the Q transition function
which deletes the current layer but I'm
still in app layer on update. I'm still
in this function that just doesn't cease
to exist. I'm inside this function and
I've deleted this instance of app layer
whose function I am inside. So why does
that even work? Because if I keep
running this program, I'll get rid of my
break point. I can keep going between
these layers with absolutely no issue.
Nothing's crashing. Everything seems to
be functioning as usual. Well, that is
just the nature of C++. That's how it
works. A function is just a function. If
it's a method inside a class, it doesn't
really matter. It's still a function.
It's not going to suddenly explode. It's
just that the actual object data has
been released now. And so, if we had
done some additional work after this
transition had taken place, this is now
gone. So basically what's happened is
we've deleted the current object over
here. That happens inside the transition
to function. So now it's dead. It's
going to keep doing whatever we want it
to do. I can print hello world over
here. I'm sorry. Let me do it the pro
way. And if I run this, that's not going
to be an issue. So there we go. I switch
from this layer to this layer. You can
see it destroyed app layer, but then it
still printed hello world because it's
going to keep running that function.
Everything's fine. What it can't do is
access data that was in app layer
because that has now been freed. that
memory is gone. So if I had done m time
plus= ts over here instead, you would
expect that to crash. So if I transition
now to something else, okay, my
application hasn't crashed. Let's have a
look at what's going on. So normally I'm
incrementing time. Time plus equals time
step. Seems fine. Here it is. Now time's
accumulated a little bit more. That's
normal. Now let's go ahead and switch
out of this. That's going to cause this
delete to happen over here. And then if
I come down to m time plus equals ts,
what's m time? Oh, it's some garbage
memory because it's been freed. The
object has been freed. I'm still going
to actually write into that memory, but
it's gone. It's doesn't belong to me
anymore. It's not my memory. However,
I'm now going to write into memory that
technically isn't mine anymore. And it's
not crashing. As you can see, I'm in
debug. This is a debug build and I'm not
crashing. Now, of course, I can
demonstrate it crashing. If we use
something a little bit more complicated,
little bit more complex like a string,
let's just say m name and I keep
assigning churn or something over here.
If I transition out of this, oh, okay,
there we go. Exception thrown. Can't do
this. It's crashed. If we run a release
build, it's not going to crash. It's
kind of dependent on exactly what you do
here because it's undefined behavior.
You don't really know what you're doing
here. You're writing to memory that
isn't yours anymore. And that's what
makes this so dangerous. The fact that
it's not just a crash. Crashes are easy.
Crashes are great when it comes to bugs
because you figure out a way to
reproduce it. You figure out the
underlying issue. You solve it. You then
try and run it again. No crash. Great.
You're done. But this there could be
code like this sitting inside your
project right now inside whatever you
work on professionally or not that is
doing this and you don't even know about
it. Now, of course, you can use tools on
top of C++ like address sanitizer, for
example, to try and make sure that
you're not doing this. However, I'm sure
a lot of you haven't run tools like
that, and I'm sure a lot of this does in
fact slip through the cracks. So, what
is the solution? Well, remember when I
said context is really important as
well. This is specifically an issue when
we transition from ourselves, right? So
when we are inside the app layer on
update and we run some code that
indirectly sort of deletes ourselves,
it's also really easy to see how exactly
this is working. If I stick a breakpoint
inside the app layer destructor and then
I cause that to happen, then I know
exactly what is destroying this object.
And if I have a look at the call stack,
then I can see that I am inside app
layer on update that calls that Q
transition function which then calls the
destructor. So within app layer on
update, I'm calling the destructor of
myself. That's what's happening here.
And if I go up the call stack over here,
you can see over here this is this is
the line of code that is causing that
destructor to run. If we show the
external code, we can also see how
that's happening from within the unique
pointer class. Now remember when I said
context is important. Context is
important because this isn't always a
bug. You could just shrug this off as
not great design. However, it's only
really a bug if we're doing it from
ourselves. And obviously if we don't
have any other code after this or we do
something like transition and then
return we are mitigating this bug
because now this I guess wouldn't cause
a crash as long as we don't do anything
in between here that might access
members and blah blah blah it could just
be one of those bad design things.
However, if we are not transitioning
this layer to another layer from within
ourselves but we're doing it externally.
So if we have a look at the overlay
layer, which is what has that button,
that switch button, you can see that
what happens when we click that switch
button is we find either the void layer
or the app layer externally because
we're in the overlay layer. So we're not
in any of these layers and we make it do
the transitioning here. And so if we
have a look at how we transition to the
void layer, for example, by clicking the
switch button inside application run,
we're iterating over the layer stack.
Yes, but the current layer is obviously
not the layer that's going to get
destroyed. It's the overlay layer. And
so when it comes to the next layer
inside the layer stack, it's going to be
our new layer. So that's kind of totally
fine. There's no real issue with this,
it will work. And that's why the context
matters. So what would be the solution
to this? Well, I would cue the
transition like the function name
indicates. I wouldn't do it immediately.
I would recognize the fact that this
could in fact happen in the middle of
our frame and it probably should never
happen in the middle of our frame. we
should probably finish what we're trying
to do and then have some kind of sync
point at the end of the frame, at the
beginning of the frame, doesn't really
matter. Over here in application, for
example, when we get to the end of our
frame, everything is done, we might have
some kind of post frame event cue that
goes through and actually does those
layer transitions because we know we're
sort of in a safe space. In more complex
architectures, this can especially be
important because if we have multiple
threads that might be persistently
running, such as like a render thread
and a main thread, we'll have this
section inside our frame where both
threads are kind of waiting for each
other. It's effectively a sync point and
that's when we can come in and do this
kind of housekeeping organizational work
because we know that we're not going to
be in the middle of existing work taking
place. I think it's fairly intuitive to
realize that if you're iterating through
layers inside the layer stack and you're
inside the onupdate function inside a
layer, you probably shouldn't allow this
very data to change. And there are clues
here just by looking at this out of
context as to something looking not
quite right. And that is that we can see
that we're dealing with unique pointers.
That's what's going on over here. So
presumably this is also a unique pointer
and we're matching that to this. So just
from the keywords this unique pointer
layer reassignment, you can kind of tell
that something is not quite right
because this implies that we are inside
a layer. Even though of course this can
just be a function that's called
externally. There's nothing obviously to
stop this from being called internally
and that's when we wind up deleting
ourselves. I hope you guys enjoyed this
video. If you did, please don't forget
to hit the like button. Has this ever
happened to you? It's definitely
happened to me before. Not in this exact
way, but accidentally deleting an object
that you are currently inside does
happen [music] from time to time. If you
guys have thoughts or ideas as to how to
mitigate this and make sure that it
doesn't happen, let me know in the
comments section below. What other bugs
have you encountered in C++? Let me know
and it might be a future episode on this
series. Thank you all for watching. I'll
see you next time. Goodbye.